Up. Down.
上、下
Left.
左
Alright.
好，可以了
Next, Osana.
下一位，長名
Right!
右！
D-Down!
下！
Left?
左嗎？
Okay, next!
好，下一位
When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所謂的“交流障礙症” 是指不擅長和人交流的一種症狀
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有這種症狀的人
-POINT… -STARTLE!
（嚇到，用手指示）
Bear in mind, they only struggle to form connections.
不過需要注意的是 這些人只是不擅長社交
It doesn't mean that they don't want to.
但並不表示他們不想和別人有往來
Komi is the prettiest, most admired girl in class.
古見同學是本班校花 是眾人仰慕的對象
Plus, she's a god.
同時她也是神
She enraptures with her beauty,
今天她同樣以那迷人的美貌
bringing joy to us commoners.
為她的屬民們帶來快樂
Oh, hi. Nice to meet you.
喔，大家好
My name is Makeru Yadano.
我的名字是矢田野真華留
I'm just a humble subject, but I have a little goal today.
雖然只是個小小屬民 現在卻有個目標
That is…
那就是…
to beat Komi at the physical exam.
在這次健康檢查上贏過古見同學
Someone is giving Komi a death glare.
有人用好可怕的表情在盯著古見同學
This physical exam has four parts.
這個健康檢查有四個項目
Vision, height, weight, seated height.
視力、身高、體重、坐高
If I can win three or more, I'll be victorious!
換句話說，在這四項當中 只要拿下三項就算我贏了
I'll beat the most superior being in our class.
贏過這班上最優秀的人
It would be my greatest achievement.
沒有比這更令人驕傲的事了
But what's this?
而且現在是怎樣？
She's not answering at all.
她從剛才就完全答不出來耶
I was unsure about the vision test,
我對視力比較沒自信
but it may be an easy win!
但看這狀況應該能輕鬆獲勝
Komi, your eyesight's above average.
好，古見，視力1.5
CAN'T SEE KOMI POINTING
（用手指方向 在背後所以看不見）
What's up with that?
這是怎麼回事？
-Komi wasn't even answering. -Y-Yadano?
-古見同學她根本沒回答啊 -矢田野同學？
Could it be, Komi…
難道說古見同學她…
bribed the examiner?
賄賂了裁判？
Unacceptable!
不可原諒！
-You'd play dirty poker just to beat me? -Hey, ow. That hurts, Yadano.
-居然使出如此卑鄙的手段想贏我 -矢田野同學，很痛耶
Fine then. I'll play fair and square.
沒關係，我就光明正大地…
And I'll beat you!
贏過妳！
BELOW AVERAGE EYESIGHT
（結果視力0.7）
You lose!
妳輸了！
HEIGHT
（身高）
WEIGHT
（體重）
SEATED HEIGHT
（坐高）
Alright, it's all measured.
全部都量完了
It's on… It's so on, Komi!
來一決勝負吧，古見同學！
ROUND 2 - HEIGHT KOMI: 168 CM
（第二回合 古見硝子，168公分）
YADANO: 156 CM
（矢田野，156公分）
Looks like I can't win this one.
這下我無法贏過她
It's fine as long as I don't lose.
不過只要不輸就行
Mine is higher!
我的數字比較大！
Yay! It's a tie…
太好了，這樣就平手了！
It's weight and seated height!
那兩項不是體重和坐高嗎？
What does that mean?
怎麼回事？
I'm shorter, but my seated height and weight are both higher?
我身高比她矮 體重和坐高數字卻比較大，是怎樣？
Hang on a minute.
可是等一下
Who decided that it's better for those to be lower?
話說回來是誰規定 體重和坐高越低越好？
In harsh lands like the savanna,
在熱帶草原那種嚴酷的環境下
people who can store fat are the winners in a food crisis.
有囤積脂肪才能對抗缺糧，才是贏家
Seated height?
那坐高呢？
There must be a place where they love short-legged women!
一定有腿短的女生比較受歡迎的國家
That's right!
沒錯，一定有！
It's a tie, Komi.
古見同學，我們平手
Incidentally, Tadano was average in every category.
順便一提 只野同學每一項都落在平均值
NO POINT MEASURING THE OBVIOUS.
（反正你怎麼量都是平均值 乾脆不要量）
MISSION 11 "IT'S JUST A CRUSH."
（任務11 是戀愛）
My name is Hitohito Tadano.
我的名字叫只野仁人
I'm an ordinary high schooler.
是個平凡的高中生
One extraordinary thing?
我唯一不平凡的一點
I'm friends with the prettiest girl in schoo--
就是我和全校第一美少女 古見同學是朋友…
My name is Ren Yamai.
我的名字叫山井戀
I'm an ordinary high schooler.
是個平凡的高中生
How ordinary, you ask?
若問我有多平凡
I don't like studying, but I love fashion!
就是我不太愛讀書，但是非常愛打扮
Good morning!
早安
I've got my worries, but I have lots of friends and I'm happy!
雖然也會有煩惱 但我有很多朋友，過得很幸福
That's ordinary, right?
這樣應該算很平凡吧？
And right now…
而這樣的我現在卻…
I have a little crush.
陷入了小小的戀愛當中
BA-BUMP…
（心動）
Komi walking.
走路的古見同學
Komi kneeling.
蹲下來的古見同學
Komi standing.
站起來的古見同學
Komi going upstairs.
上樓梯的古見同學
Komi, Komi, Komi…
古見同學…
TWITCHING
（痙攣）
Oh.
啊
Komi's so beautiful I lost myself.
討厭，古見同學太美，我頓時恍神了
Get it together!
我真是不應該
I can't stare too much or it'll be rude.
就是啊，一直盯著人家看太沒禮貌了
Ah, traces of Komi's aroma.
她身上的餘香
This color, shine, scent.
這個顏色、光澤、香味
There's no mistaking it. This is Komi's hair!
肯定不會錯，這是古見同學的頭髮
Today I'll make her mine.
決定了，我今天一定要得到她
No.
不是啦
I hope we can be friends.
我是想跟她做朋友
Calm down.
我要冷靜
Chill out, Ren Yamai.
冷靜啊，山井戀
Smile and greet her and you'll be one step closer.
只要笑嘻嘻地跟她打招呼 離朋友關係就更近一步了
Alright!
就這麼辦！
-Good morning, Kom-- -K-Komi!
-早安，古見同… -古見同學！
Good morning!
早安！
AGARI IS KOMI'S DOG.
（上理同學是古見同學的狗）
Oh no! I'm sorry.
對不起
Y-Your dog shouldn't speak to you.
我這隻狗居然跟妳說話
I-I'll be going!
我先失陪了！
What's up with her?
那女人是怎樣？
How could such an embarrassment speak to our holiness?
竟敢用那臃腫的身體 跟神聖的古見同學說話
I've got to pull myself together.
沒關係，我調整一下心情
-Komi, Good mo-- -Morning!
-古見同… -早啊！
Hey, did you see the moon last night?
我問妳，妳有看昨晚的月亮嗎？
It was so pink!
是粉紅色的耶！
And you know what?
還有啊…
Huh?
嗯？
Oh, Yamai.
啊，是山井
Morning!
早啊！
Oh, Najimi. Good morning.
馴染，早安
Ever the little chatterbox.
你今天也一樣精力過剩呢
Chatterbox?
過剩？
Komi, good morning.
古見同學，早安啊
Yeah! I did it!
好耶！成功了！
I was interrupted but I greeted Her Majesty!
雖然途中有人打擾 但我還是跟古見大人打招呼了
CREAK
（僵硬轉頭）
Oh my.
天啊
Oh, Yamai. You know…
山井，妳誤會了，這是因為…
Komi's so perfect!
古見同學好尊貴！
Huh?
什麼？
I feel so reassured.
我現在覺得好安心
Of course!
想想也是啊
I, a commoner, spoke casually to Her Majesty.
像我這種平民竟敢跟古見大人裝熟
If Her Majesty replied, she'd be selling herself short.
如果古見大人對我打招呼 那不就降低了她的格調嗎？
She ignored me and that makes me so happy!
古見大人不理會我打招呼 讓我好開心啊！
Yamai?
山井？
Najimi. Come here.
馴染，你過來一下
Huh?
什麼事？
I've been wanting to ask you, what's your relationship with Komi?
我一直就想問你 你和古見同學是什麼關係？
-Yamai, this isn't your usual-- -Just answer the question.
-妳怎麼跟平常不一樣… -少囉唆，快回答我
W-We're just friends.
我們是朋友
Oops, I sneezed.
不好意思，我突然打了個噴嚏
As if! Are you kidding me?
很勉強耶，根本沒有糊弄過去啊！
Najimi.
馴染啊
We're friends, right?
我們是朋友對吧？
So of course you'll introduce me to Komi, won't you?
那你當然會向古見同學介紹我吧？
She may kill me if I turn her down.
拒絕的話應該會被埋葬
Anyway, this is Ren Yamai.
所以我介紹一下，這位是山井戀
We played those games, remember? I'm Ren Yamai. Nice to meet you.
妳記得我們之前有一起玩嗎？ 我叫山井戀，請多指教
TREMBLE
（發抖）
Wha…
這…
RATTLE
（搖晃）
I can't handle this!
這是怎樣？
Her big, soulful eyes.
又大又圓的眼睛
Her shiny hair.
光澤柔順的毛髮
Her quivering gestures.
不停顫抖的模樣
She's like a cute little chihuahua!
簡直就跟吉娃娃一樣可愛啊！
I want to touch her! Stroke her, lick her, date her!
好想碰她，好想摸她， 好想舔她，好想跟她交往
But I can't! Her Majesty is holy!
但是不行！古見大人神聖不可侵犯
Patience… Patience Ren Yamai!
忍耐，妳要忍耐啊，山井戀！
Not yet.
現在還不是時候！
What's making Yamai do this?
是什麼讓山井激動成那樣？
Act normal.
保持平常心
Just act normal. Ren Yamai.
只要保持平常心就行了，山井戀
Hey Komi. Do you like Hamburg steak?
古見同學，我問妳 妳喜歡吃漢堡排嗎？
I made too much today for my lunch.
我今天便當做的量太多
Could you help me out by eating some?
不嫌棄的話，妳願意幫我吃一些嗎？
It's my patented Indirect Lunch Invitation!
這就是山井式 拐彎抹角約吃午飯的方式！
Of course I made the food myself.
而漢堡排當然是我親手捏製
I mixed the raw meat with my bare hands!
沒戴手套，精心捏製的漢堡排！
TADANO'S DESK
（只野同學的桌子）
You can do it!
加油！
Yeaaaah!
受不了啊！
Oh!
啊！
Oh, sorry. That was nothing.
對不起，請妳不要誤會
I mean it wasn't nothing. I'm just happy.
其實也沒誤會啦，我太高興了
So happy.
好開心
Homeroom is starting.
班會要開始了
I'll see you later, Komi.
那待會再聊囉，古見同學
TREMBLE
（發抖）
Yikes!
什麼？
What is happening?
現在是什麼狀況？
Oh, is Tadano absent today?
原來今天只野同學請假啊
When Tadano's not here, I don't know what Komi is thinking!
只野同學不在 我就根本猜不透古見同學的想法啊！
Where are you, Tadano?!
只野同學，快回來吧！
Where am I?
這是哪裡？
What is this place?
這裡是…
There's photos of Komi everywhere.
整面牆貼滿了古見同學的照片
A photocollage?
雜亂拼貼？
This must be Yamai's room.
看來這裡是山井同學的房間
What's going to happen to me?!
接下來她會對我做什麼事？
Someone!
誰來救救我啊！
Yamai!
山井
Can I go to your house today?
今天可以去妳家嗎？
Why so sudden?
幹嘛突然要來我家？
Well, you won't leave Tadano's seat even though lunch is over.
因為午休結束後 妳還待在只野同學的座位上
I figured you wanted to talk.
我在想妳可能聊得還不夠
Yes.
沒錯
I don't want to leave Komi's side.
我不想離開古見同學身邊
It was so fun spending lunch with Komi.
因為跟她共度的午休時光太快樂了
We got to talk so much.
彼此聊了好多自己的事
KOMI WAS SILENT.
（古見同學沒說話）
It was the best moment of my life.
那是我人生中最美好的一刻
I don't want to lose this moment.
我只是不想失去那一刻
Is that so wrong?!
真的那麼罪不可赦嗎？
Of course, Komi will come too.
對了，古見同學當然也會去喔
Huh?!
什麼？
K-Komi?
古見同學她…
In my room?
要去我房間？
That means her scent will get on my bed and cushions?
也就是說床和抱枕 都會沾上古見同學的香味？
Sure, of course…
好，當然可以…
Oh right, that thing's at my place.
我都忘了，家裡有那玩意兒
What should I do?
怎麼辦啊？
Komi…
古見同學…
That thing…
那玩意兒…
Sure, of course it's fine!
好，當然沒問題！
Komi won by a landslide.
古見同學獲得壓倒性勝利
It's already evening.
已經傍晚了
I'm hungry.
肚子好餓
My room is a mess. Just wait here.
我房間很亂，你們在外面等一下
Alright. Sorry for the sudden visit.
沒問題，不好意思突然跑來
She's coming!
要來了！
Yikes!
天啊！
I'm dead…
我會被殺…
PASS
（擦身而過）
Which do you prefer, the woods or the sea?
只野同學，你喜歡山還是海啊？
Th-The woods?
山？
I see.
這樣啊
That's where I'll bury you then.
那我等一下就把你埋在那裡
In the woods?
埋在山裡？
Yamai, are you done?
山井，好了嗎？
Almost!
還沒唷
My special person is coming.
待會我珍視的人會過來
If you scream I'll bury…
你要是敢出聲，我就把你埋…
Well, if you don't scream I won't bury you.
不，如果你沒出聲，我就不埋你
Okay?
聽到了嗎？
Seems like I'm dead either way.
我覺得不管聽不聽話 她都會把我埋了
Alright, come on in!
好了，請進
Go on and rub your scent on everything!
多在我房間沾上味道喔
Scent?
味道？
Is that Najimi's voice?
這是馴染的聲音？
It's Najimi!
是馴染！
Najimi! Help me!
馴染，救救我啊！
Ahaha sorry. The neighbors are so loud.
不好意思啊，隔壁住戶好吵啊
She's unphased!
也太熟練了！
What a wild neighbor.
妳家的鄰居好吵
I'll kill you, got it? Stay quiet.
當心我埋了你，給我安靜點
The woods are nearby. Shut up and obey.
這裡離山很近，你就乖乖聽話
Ha-ha. Don't worry about that.
大家不要在意喔
How can I not?!
怎麼能不在意！
I'll go make some tea. Wait here.
那我去泡茶，等我一下喔
Is jasmine tea alright?
茉莉花茶可以嗎？
Uh, sure.
喔，好啊
Don't open the closet.
不准打開衣櫥
NAJIMI OPENS IT IMMEDIATELY.
（馴染立刻就去開）
Sorry. Are we interrupting something?
抱歉，我們是不是打擾到你們了？
SOME KIND OF KINK?
（是在玩什麼變態遊戲嗎？）
Oh. You saw.
什麼嘛，被你們看到了啊
Don't misunderstand, Komi.
妳可別誤會喔，古見同學
It's not like I took out Tadano to get close to you.
我不是因為只野同學 會妨礙我接近妳才這麼做
-Cooking chopsticks! -They've been sharpened!
-長筷子！ -她拿著一把鋒利的長筷子！
It's for Komi's sake.
這都是為了古見同學好
Right?
難道不是嗎？
You're not smart or handsome. Your height and build are average.
像他這種長相和頭腦都差 身高和體格都很普通
You're not that funny and your features are plain.
既不風趣，連臉都是被隨便畫出來的
All you've got is that crappy hairstyle, Trashboy.
勉強要找出個特徵 頂多就是頭上很土的雞冠髮型
It doesn't make sense for you to be near Komi.
這種垃男圾竟敢待在天神 古見同學身邊，未免也太奇怪了吧
It hurts to be reminded.
被她那麼一說，滿受傷的
Right, Komi?
是不是？古見同學
You agree, don't you?
妳也是這麼認為的吧？
After all…
因為…
You're pretty, shapely, and classy and have a good personality,
古見同學妳長得美，身材又好 氣質高尚，個性好
and for some reason it doesn't make me jealous.
但是不知為何 看著妳卻不會讓人感到嫉妒
You complete me.
沒錯，妳就是我幸福的泉源
Why should royalty like you
在如此出色的妳身邊
be with the lowest rung of the school caste system?
卻有只野同學這種在校園階級制度 最底層的人，太奇怪了
Don't you agree, Komi?
古見同學也這麼認為吧？
You'd be happier with more popular friends.
和更有人緣的 同學做朋友比較開心吧？
So you don't need Tadano.
所以妳不需要只野同學
You need me.
妳需要的是我
I've worked hard so everyone will like me.
我有很努力獲得大家的喜愛喔
To be friends with you.
為了能成為妳的朋友
See?
妳知道嗎？
I'm the ideal friend for you, Komi.
我才最適合當妳的朋友，對吧？
You want to be my friend, don't you?
妳也很想當我的朋友吧？
Right? Komi.
是不是啊？古見同學
Huh?
什麼？
THANK YOU FOR HAVING US.
（打擾了）
So polite.
好有禮貌
W-Wait…
等一下
Wait, Komi!
古見同學，等一下！
I…
我…
I did it all for you!
我這麼做都是為了妳！
LOOKS FOR A PLACE TO WRITE
（古見同學在找地方寫字）
USES THE FLOOR
（古見同學在地板上寫字）
I CHOOSE MY OWN FRIENDS.
（我的朋友由我自己決定）
She won't even speak to me.
她連話都不願意跟我說
She hates me.
我被她討厭了
What should I do?
我該怎麼辦啊？
Tadano!
只野同學！
I feel like I forgot something.
感覺好像忘了什麼
Whatever.
算了
Komi's background!
古見同學的背景…
Is she angry?
她在生氣嗎？
Komi?
古見同學？
WE NEED TO TALK.
（我有話想說）
I guess she really is angry at me?!
我果然會被她訓斥嗎？
Um…
請問…
Komi? You wanted to talk?
古見同學，妳要跟我說什麼？
CREAK
（僵硬轉頭）
I usually know what she's thinking, but not now!
久違地看不出古見同學在想什麼
I'M NOT SURE IF I SHOULD BE YOUR FRIEND.
（我該不該繼續當你的朋友？）
What does that mean?
這是什麼意思？
YESTERDAY, YOU WENT THROUGH SOMETHING AWFUL.
（昨天你經歷那麼可怕的事）
Yeah, that's true.
也是啦
YAMAI SAID SHE DID IT FOR ME.
（山井同學說她是為了我那麼做）
THIS IS EVERYTHING YAMAI SAID.
（這是山井同學說的全部內容）
She remembers everything? Wow!
她居然全都記得？好厲害！
THIS IS ALL MY FAULT. I PUT YOU IN DANGER.
（換句話說，是因為我 才讓你遭遇了危險）
That's not tru--
沒這回事…
YES IT IS.
（就是這麼回事）
So fast!
好快！
WHAT IF WE NEVER FOUND YOU IN THAT ROOM?
（要是你一直被關在房間裡呢？）
WHAT IF SOMETHING WORSE HAPPENED?
（要是你經歷更可怕的事呢？）
WHAT IF IT HAPPENS AGAIN?
（要是下次又發生一樣的事呢？）
BECAUSE OF ME.
（都是我害的）
SO I…
（所以我…）
I DON'T THINK I SHOULD BE YOUR FRIEND.
（所以我覺得不應該 再繼續跟你做朋友了）
Oh.
嗯
Okay. I understand.
這樣啊，我瞭解了
But listen, Komi.
但是，古見同學
I choose my own friends.
我的朋友由我自己決定
BLUSH
（臉紅）
Um, no, not like that!
不是啦，不是那樣！
It's just, you know.
我沒有那個意思！
It's like what you said yesterday.
我並沒有想要學妳說過的話
I wasn't trying to sound cool.
來當作我自己耍帥的台詞
It just popped out.
我就是自然而然說出口
I wasn't trying to act cool.
我也沒有做出耍帥的表情
Just forget about it!
請妳忘了這件事吧！
I know I'm super awkward.
我自己也知道這樣很噁心
I'M SORRY.
（對不起）
Sorry about what?
幹嘛要跟我道歉啊？
I…
我…
want…
還是…
to…
想要…
be…
當…
f-friends…
當你的…
with…
你的…
you.
朋友
Yes.
好
Thank you so…
謝謝妳
Huh? Uh. Um…
那個…
Um, I also
我也一樣
want to be friends with--
想繼續跟妳做朋友…
There you are!
原來你們在這裡！
I've been looking for you!
我找了好久
Come here!
過來吧！
Yamai wants to apologize.
山井說她想道歉
To Tadano.
向只野同學道歉
Huh? To me?
什麼？向我道歉嗎？
Um, Tadano…
只野同學…
About yesterday…
昨天的事…
I'm sorry!
真的很抱歉！
I went too far.
我知道我做得太過分了
I should have just threatened you to shut you up.
其實只要恐嚇你，讓你閉嘴就行了
I'm sorry I said such terrible things.
跟你說了那麼多過分的話 真的很抱歉
That was how I felt, but I shouldn't have said them.
雖然都是我的真心話 但是不應該說出來的
I truly regret it. I'm sorry!
我有誠心反省，對不起！
She sucks at apologizing.
她不擅長道歉呢
I'm sorry to you too, Komi.
古見同學，我也要跟妳道歉
It was presumptuous of me.
我實在是太自不量力了
It's not for me to decide who should be your friend.
我憑什麼來決定誰適合當妳的朋友
This all happened because of my selfishness.
這次的事全因為我的任性而起
It'll never happen again. I'm sorry!
我絕不會再犯了，對不起！
Uh, okay.
啊，嗯
ALRIGHT.
（好的）
I guess you still…
果然還是…
You still refuse to speak to me!
連話都不願意跟我說！
A life where Komi won't speak to me
古見同學不願意跟我說話
is not a life worth living!
我活著還有什麼意義？
Where'd she get the chopstick?!
哪裡來的長筷子？
-Don't be so hasty! -Let me go, Najimi!
-山井，別衝動啊！ -馴染，快放開我！
Can I tell her about you?
古見同學 我可以把妳的事告訴她嗎？
NOD
（點頭）
Yamai!
山井同學！
Komi is just bad at talking to people.
古見同學她只是不擅長跟人往來啦
She's got bad communication skills!
她不太會跟人溝通才會這樣！
Don't be ridiculous!
那怎麼可能
Stop badmouthing Komi.
你不要說古見同學的壞話
THEY EXPLAINED THOROUGHLY.
（全都解釋清楚了）
What…
怎麼會…
So it was all a misunderstanding?
那之前都是我誤會了？
I love that Komi has such a cute side!
竟然有這麼可愛的一面啊？ 古見同學，我好喜歡妳！
Huh?
什麼？
You want to make 100 friends?
妳說妳想交100個朋友嗎？
Komi you're adorable!
古見同學，妳真可愛！
Nobody can stop Yamai.
已經沒有人能夠阻止山井同學了
Gosh, 100 friends.
這樣啊，100個朋友是嗎？
GLANCE…
（偷瞄）
Peek.
偷瞄
She just said "peek."
她說“偷瞄”耶
WANTS TO BE FRIENDS!
（山井同學看著這邊 想成為夥伴！）
What do you want to do, Komi?
古見同學，怎麼辦？
KOMI'S UNSURE!
（古見同學猶豫中！）
Understandable.
這也難怪
L-LET'S BE FRIENDS.
（那就請多多關照了）
Yes! A thousand times yes!
沒問題！請多關照，古見同學！
FANTASY
（想像畫面）
-I'LL DIE IF KOMI HATES ME! -THERE, THERE. WE'LL APOLOGIZE TOMORROW.
（-我被古見同學討厭，只能去死了 -乖，妳不用去死，明天去道歉吧）
If you touch Komi I'll bury you.
如果你敢染指古見同學 當心我埋了你
Yamai is obsessed.
山井同學有著病態的迷戀
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：馬慈光